<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>PinNotes – IITM BS Degree</title><link>/tags/iitm-bs-degree/</link><description>Recent content in IITM BS Degree on PinNotes</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/iitm-bs-degree/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Frequently Asked Questions</title><link>/blog/iit/iitm-bg-degree-faq/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/iit/iitm-bg-degree-faq/</guid><description>
&lt;h2&gt;IIT Madras BS Degree in Data Science and Applications: Frequently Asked Questions&lt;span class="hx-absolute -hx-mt-20" id="iit-madras-bs-degree-in-data-science-and-applications-frequently-asked-questions"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#iit-madras-bs-degree-in-data-science-and-applications-frequently-asked-questions" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3&gt;What is the IIT Madras BS Degree in Data Science and Applications programme?&lt;span class="hx-absolute -hx-mt-20" id="what-is-the-iit-madras-bs-degree-in-data-science-and-applications-programme"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#what-is-the-iit-madras-bs-degree-in-data-science-and-applications-programme" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is an online programme offering various exit points, allowing learners to earn a Foundation level certificate, Diploma in Programming, Diploma in Data Science, a BSc degree in Programming and Data Science, or a BS degree in Data Science and Applications from IIT Madras. The course content is delivered online, but monthly quizzes and final semester exams require in-person attendance at designated centres. The programme is open to individuals of any background and age, with no geographical limitations on learning besides exam centre travel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What are the different levels and qualifications offered within the programme?&lt;span class="hx-absolute -hx-mt-20" id="what-are-the-different-levels-and-qualifications-offered-within-the-programme"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#what-are-the-different-levels-and-qualifications-offered-within-the-programme" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The programme is structured in four levels, each building upon the previous one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Level 1: The Foundation level:&lt;/strong&gt; Comprises 8 foundational courses (32 credits) covering subjects like English, Mathematics, Statistics, Computational Thinking, and Introduction to Python. Successful completion earns a Foundation level certificate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Level 2: Diploma level:&lt;/strong&gt; Includes two distinct diplomas: Diploma in Programming and Diploma in Data Science. Each diploma consists of 6 courses (23 credits) and 2 project courses (4 credits), totalling 54 credits for both diplomas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Level 3: BSc Degree level:&lt;/strong&gt; Requires completion of the Foundation and Diploma levels, totalling 114 credits. This level includes mandatory core courses, a professional growth course, and allows for some credits from NPTEL courses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Level 4: BS Degree level:&lt;/strong&gt; Requires completion of 142 credits, building upon the BSc level. This level offers options for apprenticeship credits and includes mandatory level 4 courses in both programming and data science streams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How can someone gain admission to the programme?&lt;span class="hx-absolute -hx-mt-20" id="how-can-someone-gain-admission-to-the-programme"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#how-can-someone-gain-admission-to-the-programme" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are two main entry pathways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regular Entry into Foundation level:&lt;/strong&gt; Applicants must pass a Qualifier exam. Eligibility for the Qualifier exam is based on achieving minimum average scores in weekly assignments in the four initial subjects over a 4-week period. The Qualifier exam itself requires meeting minimum individual subject cut-offs and a total cut-off score. Qualifier scores are valid for 3 subsequent terms for registration to the Foundation level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;JEE-based Entry into Foundation Level:&lt;/strong&gt; Students who have qualified for the JEE Advanced Exams can gain direct entry into the Foundation level. They need to apply through the Qualifier process and provide valid proof of their JEE Advanced eligibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, there is a &lt;strong&gt;Direct Entry into Diploma programme&lt;/strong&gt; pathway primarily aimed at working professionals or those with existing fundamentals. This requires completing 2 years of any undergraduate degree programme and passing a separate Direct Admission to Diploma (DAD) qualifier exam for either the Diploma in Programming or the Diploma in Data Science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What are the fees for the programme, and are there any fee waivers?&lt;span class="hx-absolute -hx-mt-20" id="what-are-the-fees-for-the-programme-and-are-there-any-fee-waivers"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#what-are-the-fees-for-the-programme-and-are-there-any-fee-waivers" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fees vary depending on the level of study and the number of credits taken in a term. The Qualifier exam has a non-refundable entry fee of Rs. 3000, with suitable waivers available. Fee waivers are offered based on the learner&amp;rsquo;s category (General, EWS, OBC, SC/ST, PwD) and family income. The programme is designed with lower first-year fees to encourage initial participation. Specific fee structures for each level and cost per credit are detailed in the handbook, including separate facilitation fees for students taking exams outside India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How is the Credit Clearing Capability (CCC) determined, and how does it affect course registration?&lt;span class="hx-absolute -hx-mt-20" id="how-is-the-credit-clearing-capability-ccc-determined-and-how-does-it-affect-course-registration"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#how-is-the-credit-clearing-capability-ccc-determined-and-how-does-it-affect-course-registration" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The CCC determines the maximum number of courses a learner is permitted to register for in a term. For the first term, it is decided by Qualifier marks. From the second term onwards, the CCC is calculated based on the average marks of courses passed in the preceding terms. If a learner fails all courses in a term, their CCC for the next term is set to 2. While the CCC is enforced for most learners, for students in the Foundation level from May 2024 onwards, the CCC will be a recommendation to allow them flexibility in meeting new course completion checkpoints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is the academic calendar and how does course registration work?&lt;span class="hx-absolute -hx-mt-20" id="what-is-the-academic-calendar-and-how-does-course-registration-work"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#what-is-the-academic-calendar-and-how-does-course-registration-work" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The academic year is divided into three terms: January-April, May-August, and September-December. Foundation, Diploma level courses, and mandatory BSc level courses are offered every term. Learners can register for courses based on their CCC, subject to fulfilling prerequisite requirements. Students cannot register for courses across different levels in the same term. The minimum duration for completing any level is 36 months (3 years/9 terms), and the entire programme must be completed within 96 months (8 years/24 terms). Course registration is done online, and payment is made per credit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How are courses graded and what are the passing criteria?&lt;span class="hx-absolute -hx-mt-20" id="how-are-courses-graded-and-what-are-the-passing-criteria"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#how-are-courses-graded-and-what-are-the-passing-criteria" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Courses are graded using an absolute grading system based on the Total Course Score (T), which is the sum of all assessment components. A candidate passes a course if their Total Course Score is 40/100 or higher. Letter grades from S (highest) to E (lowest passing grade) and U (fail) are awarded based on score ranges. GPA is calculated per term, and CGPA is computed for all unique courses completed, with the best grade being considered in case of multiple attempts. Project courses have specific grading criteria, including L1 and L2 vivas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What are the policies regarding repeating or dropping courses and academic progression?&lt;span class="hx-absolute -hx-mt-20" id="what-are-the-policies-regarding-repeating-or-dropping-courses-and-academic-progression"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#what-are-the-policies-regarding-repeating-or-dropping-courses-and-academic-progression" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Learners can repeat a course for improvement in grades any number of times, with the highest score being considered for CGPA calculation (though repeating for improvement after completing diplomas may not count for prizes). Repeating a course for improvement incurs double the regular course fee. Learners can also repeat courses if they receive a failing grade (U, WA, WQ) or an Incomplete (I) grade. An Incomplete grade may allow for a Make-Up Exam in the subsequent term instead of repeating the entire course. Dropping a course is permitted within the first 4 weeks of a term, with a portion of the fee being retained as an administrative charge and the rest credited to the student wallet for future course registration. Specific checkpoints and maximum time limits for completing each level are in place, with failure to meet these potentially leading to academic probation or removal from the programme. To progress to the BSc level from May 2024 onwards, students must achieve a CGPA of 6.0 or higher at the end of the two diplomas and a CGPA of 7.0 or higher in all completed diploma level projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NotebookLM can be inaccurate; please double-check its responses.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How can students enter the programme?</title><link>/blog/iit/how-can-student-enter-the-programme/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/iit/how-can-student-enter-the-programme/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;Certainly. The IIT Madras BS in Data Science &amp;amp; Applications programme offers multiple pathways for students to enter, primarily through a Qualifier process or direct entry routes based on previous qualifications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the ways students can enter the programme, based on the provided sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regular Entry into Foundation Level (via Qualifier Exam)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is a primary method for most applicants to enter the programme.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eligibility to Apply for the Qualifier Exam:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Applicants must have studied Mathematics and English in Class 10.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone who has passed Class 12 or equivalent is eligible to apply, regardless of age or academic background. Those who qualify can join immediately.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;School students who have appeared for their Class 11 final exams can also apply, irrespective of their stream or board. If they qualify, they can join after passing Class 12.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Qualifier Process:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regular entry applicants must undergo a 4-week process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access is provided to content for four Foundation level courses: English 1, Maths-1, Statistics-1, and Computational Thinking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weekly graded assignments are released and must be submitted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eligibility to Appear for the Qualifier Exam:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Based on the average score of weekly assignments in each of the four subjects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minimum average assignment scores are required to get the hall ticket for the in-person proctored exam. These minimums vary by candidate category (General, SC/ST/PwD, OBC-NCL/EWS).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Passing the Qualifier Exam:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An in-person proctored exam is conducted at the end of the 4 weeks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To pass, a learner must obtain marks equal to or greater than the individual subject cut-off &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the total score across all subjects must be greater than the total cut-off. The cut-off marks are specified based on the candidate&amp;rsquo;s category.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Upon Qualification:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Candidates who qualify are intimated via email, WhatsApp, and within their portal login. An admission letter is also provided.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It is important to note&lt;/strong&gt; that passing the Qualifier is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; admission to a degree programme. It makes the learner eligible to register for the set of Foundation courses. Diplomas or degrees are earned only by accruing the requisite number of credits by completing prescribed courses and satisfying other mandatory criteria.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The qualifier score is valid for the three subsequent terms for registration to the Foundation level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Candidates who qualify in the first attempt within a term can register for courses in the same term (where the qualifier score counts as Quiz 1) or in the next two terms. Those who qualify in the second attempt within a term can &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; register from the subsequent term.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reattempting the Qualifier:&lt;/strong&gt; There are two attempts within any term. Candidates who were eligible for the hall ticket but were absent or failed the first attempt can re-attempt the exam by paying a fee. Candidates who did not become eligible for the qualifier exam must redo the 4-week process and pay the full fees for a fresh application in a subsequent term. There is no limit on the number of times a candidate can attempt the qualifier process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;JEE-based Entry into Foundation Level&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This offers a &lt;strong&gt;direct entry&lt;/strong&gt; into the Foundation level for students who have qualified for the JEE Advanced Exams.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The validity of this direct entry is for the three terms following the release of the JEE Advanced Eligibility list.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Process:&lt;/strong&gt; Applicants apply to the Qualifier process, indicate their eligibility for JEE Advanced, and upload valid proof.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outcome:&lt;/strong&gt; If the proof is valid, the candidate is declared eligible to join the Foundational level courses, issued an admission letter, and can directly register for courses with a Credit Clearing Capability (CCC) of 4. If the proof is invalid, the candidate is moved to the regular entry category and must go through the standard qualifier process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Direct Entry into Diploma Programme (DAD)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This pathway is designed for working professionals or learners who already possess the fundamental knowledge taught in the Foundation level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The entry point is directly into the Diploma level. The potential exit point from this route is one or both Diplomas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eligibility to Apply:&lt;/strong&gt; Students who have completed two years in any undergraduate degree programme are permitted to apply for direct entry to the Diploma level. Proof, such as their second-year marksheet or higher, must be submitted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Qualifying Process:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A separate Direct Admission to Diploma (DAD) qualifier exam is conducted. These exams happen three times a year, coinciding with the programme&amp;rsquo;s end-term examinations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are separate DAD qualifier exams for the Diploma in Programming (DAD-DP) and the Diploma in Data Science (DAD-DS).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The DAD-DP qualifier is a 3-hour exam covering English, Aptitude, and 6 weeks of Maths 1 content. Students who pass this would then study Computational Thinking, Introduction to Python before starting the Programming Diploma subjects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The DAD-DS qualifier is a 4-hour exam covering English, Maths 1, Statistics 1, and Python programming. Students who pass this would then start with Maths 2 and Statistics 2 before continuing with Data Science Diploma subjects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Candidates must cross the defined cut-off marks in the DAD Qualifier exam to be eligible. Cut-off marks vary by category.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Passing the DAD-DS qualifier makes a student eligible to pursue the Diploma in Programming without a further qualifier, but passing the DAD-DP qualifier requires sitting the DAD-DS qualifier if the student wishes to pursue the Diploma in Data Science (because Maths 1 and Statistics 1 were not part of the DAD-DP exam).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, students can initially enter the IITM BS programme through a regular Qualifier exam process for the Foundation level, a direct entry route into the Foundation level for eligible JEE Advanced candidates, or a direct entry route into the Diploma level via a separate DAD qualifier exam.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>IIT Madras Data Science Programme:- Timeline and Cast</title><link>/blog/iit/iitm-bs-degree-timeline/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/iit/iitm-bs-degree-timeline/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;Timeline of IIT Madras BS in Data Science &amp;amp; Applications Programme
This timeline outlines the significant events and policy changes within the IIT Madras BS in Data Science &amp;amp; Applications programme, based on the provided student handbook excerpts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recurring Events (Occur multiple times per year/term):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Term Start: The programme operates on a three-term academic calendar: January-April, May-August, and September-December.
Course Delivery: Course content is delivered online throughout each term.
Weekly Assignments: Students are required to complete weekly assignments for enrolled courses.
Quizzes: Two quizzes are conducted per term for each course. At least one must be attended to be eligible for the final exam. For students taking the Qualifier exam in the first attempt within a term, the qualifier score can be treated as the Quiz 1 score.
In-Person Exams: Monthly quizzes and final semester exams must be attended in-person at designated centres.
Qualifier Exam (Regular Entry): Conducted at the end of 4 weeks and again at the end of 8 weeks in every term for eligible candidates based on assignment scores.
Direct Admission to Diploma (DAD) Qualifier Exam: Conducted three times a year on the same date as the end-term examinations.
Registration Window Closes: Adding courses is not allowed after this point in a term.
Dropping a Course: Permitted within the first 4 weeks of a term start date. Fees are partially refunded to the student wallet.
Final End Term Exam: A 1.5-hour in-person exam for each course conducted at the end of a term. Accounts for 50% of the Total Course Score.
Make Up Exams: Offered in the subsequent term for courses with an &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo; (Incomplete) grade.
Repeat Courses: Students can repeat courses for improvement or if they received certain failing or incomplete grades.
Credit Transfer for NPTEL Courses: Can be applied for in the BSc/BS levels after completing NPTEL courses using the official IITM email. Process involves registering for the NPTEL exam, paying fees, and submitting an undertaking.
Senate Meetings: Conducted three or four times a year for approval before generating original certificates.
Certificate Delivery: Provisional and Original certificates are delivered after specific cut-off dates depending on the term of completion.
Specific Events and Policy Implementation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;September 2021 Term (and before): Projects were included within theory courses for some students completing diplomas. For these students, only standalone projects (if any) completed at the diploma level will be counted towards the 7.0 CGPA eligibility criterion for entering the degree level.
January 2024:Credit Transfer from courses conducted on the IITM campus comes into effect.
BDM project evaluation changes to allow web scraping and analysis of data, with a maximum grade of D in this specific scenario.
Changes in project grading (MAD1, MAD2, MLP) are in effect.
Students who entered the Foundation or Diploma level in this term or before are not subject to the new completion checkpoints for these levels (applicable from May 2024).
Students who qualified for JEE Advanced 2022 can directly join the Foundation level in this term (validity for JEE Advanced 2022 qualification started in Sep 2023).
May 2024:Eligibility criteria for entering the BSc level based on a minimum CGPA of 6.0 in diplomas and 7.0 in diploma projects comes into effect for all students entering the degree level from this term.
New completion checkpoints for students admitted to the Foundation level are applicable from this term. Students will be removed from the programme if they do not complete a minimum number of courses within specified terms.
New checkpoints for students admitted to the Diploma level are applicable from this term. Students will be put on academic probation or removed from the programme if they do not complete a minimum number of courses and projects within specified terms.
The Credit Clearing Capability (CCC) in the Foundation level becomes a recommendation rather than being strictly enforced for all students in the Foundation level (including those who entered before May 2024).
Students who qualified for JEE Advanced 2023 can directly join the Foundation level in this term (validity for JEE Advanced 2023 qualification started in Sep 2023).
September 2024 Term: New cities are added for exam centres. Students who qualified for JEE Advanced 2023 can directly join the Foundation level in this term.
January 2025 Term: Students who qualified for JEE Advanced 2023 can directly join the Foundation level in this term (the final term of validity for JEE Advanced 2023 qualification).
Programme Structure Milestones:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Foundation Level Completion: Requires successfully completing 8 courses (32 credits). Makes a learner eligible to enter the Diploma level.
Diploma Level Completion: Requires successfully completing 6 courses (23 credits) and 2 project courses (4 credits) for each diploma (Programming and/or Data Science). Total of 54 credits for both. Successful completion makes a learner eligible for admission to the degree level (if other criteria are met). The maximum duration for completing the Diploma level is extended to 12 terms (applicable to all learners from the first batch who started in Sep 2021).
BSc Degree Level Completion: Requires completing 114 credits as per the norms. Students who complete this level and quit the programme receive Alumnus status.
BS Degree Level Completion: Requires completing 142 credits as per the norms. Includes the option of an Apprenticeship (4 or 12 credits) and mandatory credits from the HS/MG stream. Students who complete this level and quit the programme receive Alumnus status.
Minor in Economics and Finance Completion: Can be earned only with the BS degree by completing 2 mandatory courses and one elective course.
Learner Life Cycle Stages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the rolls/Active: When a learner is registered for one or more courses in a term.
On Academic Probation: When a learner skips up to 2 consecutive terms without taking courses, or for students admitted to the Diploma level from May 2024 who don&amp;rsquo;t meet the checkpoint criteria in the first 3 terms.
Struck off the rolls: If a learner on Academic Probation for 2 consecutive terms does not register in the next term. Requires re-admission fee and payment of pending RKA fees (with penalty) to reactivate registration. Removed from the programme if struck off twice.
Quit the programme: Learner explicitly chooses to leave the programme. No reactivation for continuing is possible.
Alumnus: Learners who complete the BSc or BS level and quit the programme.
FL certified, DS certified, DP certified, Both diplomas certified: Status for learners completing Foundation or Diploma level(s) and quitting, without achieving Alumnus status.
Prize Eligibility Milestones:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Completing Foundation + 2 Diplomas (86 credits): Eligible for Certificate of Merit (CGPA 9.00-9.50), Certificate of Academic Distinction (CGPA &amp;gt; 9.50), and Certificate of Academic Excellence (Highest CGPA).
Graduating with BS Degree (142 credits): Eligible for Certificate of Merit (CGPA 9.00-9.50), Certificate of Academic Distinction (CGPA &amp;gt; 9.50), and Certificate of Academic Excellence (Highest CGPA).
Completing Diplomas through Direct Admission: Eligible for prizes only in the highest CGPA category.
Cast of Characters
Based on the provided text, the principal entities and roles mentioned are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IIT Madras BS Degree Office: The administrative body responsible for the Data Science &amp;amp; Applications programme. Located at the ICSR Building, IIT Madras, Chennai.
IIT Madras: The institution offering the BS in Data Science and Applications programme. Its faculty teaches courses in the programme.
Students/Learners/Candidates/Applicants: Individuals participating in or applying to the programme. They progress through different levels and statuses within the programme.
Faculty of IIT Madras/Other Reputed Institutes: Educators who teach the courses in the programme.
Experts from the Industry: Professionals who contribute to teaching courses in the programme.
Admin team: Responsible for administrative tasks, including scheduling system compatibility tests.
Exam vendor: The external entity responsible for booking slots for in-person quizzes and final exams in designated cities.
BDM team: The group responsible for outlining the steps involved in the changed BDM project evaluation process.
Steering committee: Decides the actual number of students awarded the Certificate of Academic Excellence.
Companies: Potential partners for Apprenticeships offered at the BS level, with the option to provide pre-placement offers.
Brief Bios (based on roles and responsibilities in the document):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IIT Madras BS Degree Office: Acts as the central administrative hub for the programme, providing support, managing policies, and overseeing regulations and procedures.
IIT Madras: The overarching educational institution that has designed and launched the online BS programme, providing the academic framework, faculty expertise, and degree certification.
Students/Learners/Candidates/Applicants: The participants in the programme, ranging from those applying for the Qualifier exam to those pursuing the BS degree. They navigate the programme&amp;rsquo;s structure, course requirements, and policies.
Faculty of IIT Madras/Other Reputed Institutes &amp;amp; Experts from the Industry: The instructional staff who deliver the course content, bringing academic and practical knowledge to the learners.
Admin team: Handles practical and logistical aspects of the programme&amp;rsquo;s operation, ensuring necessary technical checks are performed.
Exam vendor: A third-party service provider facilitating the in-person examination process across different locations.
BDM team: A specialised group within the programme administration responsible for defining and managing the evaluation process for the Business Data Management project.
Steering committee: A decision-making body responsible for determining the number of top-performing students who receive the highest academic honour.
Companies: External organisations that collaborate with the programme to provide real-world work experience opportunities through apprenticeships for BS-level students.
NotebookLM can be inaccurate; please double-check its responses.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>What is the structure and progression through the IITM BS Degree levels?</title><link>/blog/iit/structure-and-progression-through-the-iitm-bs-degree-levels/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/iit/structure-and-progression-through-the-iitm-bs-degree-levels/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;The IIT Madras BS in Data Science &amp;amp; Applications programme is structured across four distinct levels, offering multiple entry and exit points. The course content is delivered online, though monthly quizzes and final semester exams are conducted in-person at designated centres.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an overview of the structure and progression through the levels:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Programme Structure and Levels&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Level 1: The Foundation Level&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is the initial entry point for most applicants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It comprises 8 courses: English 1, English 2, Mathematics 1, Mathematics 2, Statistics 1, Statistics 2, Computational Thinking, and Introduction to Python.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Successful completion of these 8 courses is required to register for Year 2 Diploma level courses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Foundation level accounts for 32 credits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learners can earn a Foundation level certificate upon completion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Level 2: Diploma Level&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This level includes two distinct Diplomas: Diploma in Programming and Diploma in Data Science.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diploma in Programming:&lt;/strong&gt; Consists of 6 courses (23 credits) and 2 project courses (4 credits). Courses include Database Management Systems (DBMS), Programming Data Structures and Algorithms using Python (PDSA), Java programming, System Commands, Application Development - 1, and Application Development - 2, plus project courses in Application Development.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diploma in Data Science:&lt;/strong&gt; Consists of 6 courses (23 credits) and 2 project courses (4 credits). Courses include Machine Learning Foundations (MLF), Machine Learning Techniques (MLT), Machine Learning Practice (MLP), Business Data Management (BDM), Business Analytics (BA), and Tools in Data Science (TDS), plus project courses in Business Data Management and Machine Learning Practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each diploma comprises a total of 27 credits (23 course credits + 4 project credits).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The combined Diploma level totals 54 credits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learners can earn a Diploma in Programming, a Diploma in Data Science, or both upon completion of the respective requirements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Successful completion of &lt;strong&gt;all 8 Foundation courses and the 12 Diploma level courses + 4 project courses&lt;/strong&gt; is necessary before registering for Year 3 Degree level courses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Level 3: BSc Degree Level&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This level requires a total of 28 credits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It includes mandatory core pairs (Software Engineering, Software Testing, Artificial Intelligence, and Deep Learning) and a mandatory course: Strategies for Professional Growth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A maximum of 4 credits can be obtained from NPTEL courses in the technical bucket.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The total credits required to graduate with the BSc degree are 114. Learners become eligible for the BSc degree upon completing 114 credits according to norms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Level 4: BS Degree Level&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is the final level, requiring a total of 28 credits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It offers the option of an Apprenticeship, allowing learners to earn 0, 4, 8, or 12 credits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is mandatory to earn 4 credits from the HS/MG stream, which can be from NPTEL or programme electives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mandatory completion of 2 Level 4 courses in the programming stream and 2 Level 4 courses in the data science stream is required.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The total credits required to graduate with the BS degree are 142. Learners become eligible for the BS degree upon completing 142 credits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Minor in Economics and Finance can be earned by completing 2 mandatory courses (Corporate Finance and Managerial Economics) and one elective course, credited within the 142 credits for the BS degree. The Minor can only be earned with the BS degree.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Progression Through Levels&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Entry into Foundation Level:&lt;/strong&gt; Applicants must generally pass a Qualifier exam. There is also a direct entry route for students who have qualified for the JEE Advanced Exams.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Progression from Foundation to Diploma Level:&lt;/strong&gt; Requires successful completion of all courses in the Foundation level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Progression from Diploma to BSc Degree Level:&lt;/strong&gt; Learners who successfully complete all courses in the Foundation and Diploma programmes become eligible for admission to the degree level if they satisfy the prescribed/regulatory criteria. For students admitted to the Diploma level from May 2024 onwards, eligibility requires securing a CGPA of 6.0 or higher at the end of the two diplomas (including Foundation and Diploma courses/projects) &lt;strong&gt;AND&lt;/strong&gt; a CGPA of 7.0 or higher specifically in all diploma-level projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Progression from BSc to BS Degree Level:&lt;/strong&gt; Students who complete 114 credits as per the norms are eligible for the BSc degree and can then continue onto the BS level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Credit Definition:&lt;/strong&gt;
Credits in this programme are based on the UGC system, where &lt;strong&gt;14 hours of learner engagement counts as 1 credit&lt;/strong&gt;. This is equivalent to 3 credits in the current IITM campus Credit system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Entry and Exit Points:&lt;/strong&gt;
The programme is designed with two entry points (Regular Entry into Foundation, JEE-based Entry into Foundation, and Direct Entry into Diploma) and four potential exit points, allowing learners to leave with course certificates, one or both diplomas, a BSc degree, or the final BS degree. It is important to note that passing the Qualifier exam allows entry into the Foundation courses, not automatic admission to a degree programme; diplomas or degrees are earned by accruing the requisite credits and satisfying mandatory criteria.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>